YESENIA ROMÁN

Los Angeles, CA, US ● (939) 207 -8641 romanloyesenia@gmail.com

Summary

I am a creative, resourceful, and bilingual librarian with over seven years of experience in reference, data acquisition, and cataloging services at large research institutions, and most recently at a public library. I enjoy helping people conduct research, learn, and make discoveries.

Professional experience

General Services Librarian, Part-time Inglewood Public Library, Main Library, Inglewood, CA.

June 2022 - Present

- ♦ Provide reference services and technological assistance for patrons of all ages.
- ♦ Develop and lead community programming to engage and educate the public.
- ♦ Curate book displays to showcase the collection.
- ♦ Design promotional materials for programs, events, and social media.

Research Librarian April 2021- Aug. 2021
Prof. Curtis Deutsch Computational Laboratory, University of Washington (Remote, contract-based)

- ♦ Conducted a systematic literature review in Proquest and Web of Science for laboratory mea-
- ♦ Created a database of measurements extracted from published articles, tables, and figures.
- ♦ Organized citations and sources on Zotero shared library.

surements of marine species thermal growth curves.

Research Librarian II (Data Services Specialist II)
Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

Jan. 2019 - Oct. 2020

- ♦ Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.
- ♦ Data acquisition for six-plus research teams, leading to authorship in a peer-reviewed scientific article.
- Acquired and cataloged hundreds of data sources in differ- ent languages and formats.
- Advised and taught researchers best practices of data management and seeking.
- ♦ Established relationships with global vendors, researchers, and data providers in English and Spanish, leading to long-lasting data sharing and research collaborations between diverse organizations.

Research Librarian I (Data Services Specialist I)
Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2019

- ♦ Managed the Institute's Help Desk, including supervising task delegation and resource allocation for 6 librarians
- ♦ Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.

♦ Data acquisition for three annual studies by six-plus research teams, leading to my authorship in five peer-reviewed scientific articles.

Data Curator Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA Dec. 2015 - Jan. 2017

- ♦ Dataset archiving in multiple formats and languages for an online public access catalog (GHDx) to ensure user agreement compliance.
- ♦ Managed Institute's catalog journal taxonomy by performing monthly reviews, additions, and merges.
- ♦ Biannual data source updates.

Digital Content Curator Market.Space Inc, (Remote)

Nov. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- ♦ Reviewed and created metadata for news articles on trav- el, venture capital, and gaming to train a machine-learning algorithm.
- ♦ Documented observations for taxonomy development and review.

Additional Experience

UX Research Assistant (June 2015 - Aug 2015)

Library of Congress: Office of Strategic Initiatives, Washington, DC

Web services Graduate Assistant (Aug 2013 - May 2015)

Social sciences, Health, and Education Library, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL

Special Education Paraprofessional (March 2013 - July 2013)

Chicago Tech Academy, Chicago, IL

Education

M.S. in Library and Information Sciences, Data Curation specialization

University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

B.A. in Mesoamerican and Caribbean Anthropology

University of Puerto Rico, San Juan

Skills

Languages: English (Fluent) • Spanish (Native)

Microsoft Office Excel/Google Sheets

Adobe Illustrator/Procreate/Canvas

Intermediate knowledge of HTML and CSS.

Metadata skills

Project management

Cataloging

Reference

Bibliographic Research

Documentation